Designing cost functions is difficult and getting them
设计成本函数是比较困难的工作
all to cooperate to produce reasonable vehicle behavior is hard.
而将它们组合起来以生成可用的车辆行为则是非常困难的工作
Some of the difficulties associated with cost functions design
其中的一些困难与成本函数设计相关
include solving new problems without unsolving old ones.
包括既要解决新问题 又不会影响老问题
When you're working on a self-driving car,
当你从事与无人驾驶车有关的工作时
you may find that the vehicle is behaving reasonably
你也许会发现 车辆行为还可以
well except for some particular situations.
但是一些特定情况除外
Maybe it's not being aggressive enough about making left turns at traffic lights.
比如 在交通信号灯处 车辆可能畏畏缩缩 不敢大胆左转
So, in an effort to solve this problem,
于是 为了解决这个问题
you either add new cost functions,
你添加了新的成本函数
tweak existing ones, or modify the weights.
或者修改了当前使用的成本函数 或者修改了权重
But every time you do,
但是 你每次去做这些的时候
there's a chance that you will introduce
很可能 你会把新问题
some breaking change into something that already works.
带入已经工作得很好的原有模块中
In practice, we solve this through regression testing,
实践中 我们通过回归测试来解决这个问题
where we define some set of situations,
我们定义了一些场景
each of which has an expected behavior.
每个场景都有预期行为
Then, whenever we make a change,
接下来 每当我们做出改变
we simulate the vehicle in all of
我们运行所有测试用例来进行测试
our test cases and make sure that it still behaves as expected.
确保车辆依然还保持预期行为
We won't say more about testing here,
关于测试 我们这里不展开论述
but it is an important part of developing software in a safety-critical application.
但是测试是很重要的部分
The next difficulty is balancing costs of drastically different magnitudes.
另一个困难是 如何去平衡各种目标量之间的冲突
Because, yes, we want to get to our destination efficiently,
比如 我们想要高效地到达目的地
but if we are in a situation where safety is an issue,
但是如果我们处于这样一个场景 在那里安全是个重要问题
we want to solve that problem and not think about efficiency at all.
那么 我们会解决安全问题 而忽略效率
One way to do that is to have weights which
这方面的一种解决方法是定义权重
reflect the type of problem the cost function addresses.
权重反映出成本函数相关问题的类型
So we want to most heavily penalize
比如 我们不会考虑
any behavior which simply isn't possible due to physics,
任何物理上不可行的行为
then we want to think about safety, legality, comfort.
然后我们还要考虑安全性 合规性 舒适性
And only once those are satisfied do we want to think about efficiency.
当这些目标全部满足后 我们才会考虑高效性
But we also may want to adjust
但是我们也会根据情况 来调整
the relative importance of these weights depending on situation.
这些权重的相对重要性
If a light turns red, for example,
例如 如果红灯亮了
legality becomes a much more relevant concern
与进入一般高速驾驶模式相比
than when we engage in normal highway driving.
合规性就变得非常重要
And this leads us to our last difficulty,
这引出了我们最后一个困难
reasoning about individual cost functions.
那就是 如何推导出每一个成本函数
Ideally, each cost function will serve a very specific responsibility,
理想情况下 每个成本函数负责某个特定方面
which is something we didn't do in our earlier example of a speed cost function.
这些方面是我们之前在速度成本函数例子中没有涉及的东西
We were trying to balance our desire to drive quickly,
我们想要在高速高效行驶和不超速之间
which has to do with efficiency,
获取一种平衡
with our desire to not exceed the speed limit, which is legality.
超速行为涉及到合规性
In practice, we might want to define
实践中 我们也许会定义
several cost functions associated with vehicle speed.
几个成本函数 并和速度相关联
In which case we might have a binary cost function which just checks to see if we are
在上述例子中 我们或许会定义一个二态成本函数
breaking the speed limit and the continuous
用来检测是否超速
cost function which pulls us towards our target speed.
还有一个连续性成本函数 用来将车速调到目标车速
By assigning each cost function to a very specific role,
通过给特定规则定义一个成本函数
like safety versus legality versus efficiency,
比如 安全性 合规性 高效性
we can then standardize the output of all cost functions to be between -1 and 1.
我们可以标准化所有成本函数的输出值 让结果位于-1和1之间
Additionally, it's helpful to parametrize whenever possible.
另外 尽可能参数化也是很有用的
This allows us to use some parameter optimization technique like
这样我们可以使用一些参数优化技术
gradient descent along with our set of
比如 梯度下降 加上我们的回归测试集
regression tests to programmatically tweak our cost functions.
来用程序调整我们的成本函数
Finally, thinking in terms of vehicle state is helpful.
最后 通过车辆状态来思考问题也很有用
The things we can indirectly control about
我们能用来间接控制车辆的参数有
our vehicle are its position, velocity, and acceleration.
位置 速度 加速度等
It can be helpful to keep these in mind when coming up with cost functions.
构造成本函数时候 脑子里想着这些东西会很有帮助
Let's walk through an example.
我们来看一个例子
Say we want to think about the following classes of cost functions.
假设我们想要考虑以下类型的成本函数
And to make it easier,
为了让我们的思考
to keep everything straight,
容易和直观一点
let's think in terms of position, velocity, and acceleration.
我们就来考虑位置 速度 和加速度
The binary "Are we exceeding the speed?"
“是否超速”就是一个二态问题
cost function would go here,
对应的成本函数在这里
then the cost function that wanted to keep us close to the speed limit would go here.
然后 让我们保持速度接近限制值的成本函数在这里
And now, instead of being that weird discontinuous graph we made earlier,
现在 我们不用之前看起来比较怪异的不连续图形
this could just be some parabola like this.
这次的图形是像这样的抛物线
And even though the cost of this is low even for speeds that exceed the speed limit,
这里 尽管这个点的成本是低的 但是需要超过限速
that's OK because we have our binary cost function which would prevent that behavior.
那也没什么问题 因为我们的二元成本函数将阻止它
Continuing to think about speed,
我们来继续思考速度
we also might want to try to drive at
我们试图在某个速度上行驶
a speed that's close to the average speed of traffic,
这个速度接近所有车辆的平均速度
for safety reasons, even if that speed is above or below the speed limit.
安全起见 哪怕这个速度比限速稍高或者略低
And that would go here.
然后这个成本函数将会在这里定义
In the position column,
在位置栏这里
we'd have an obvious feasibility concern which is collision avoidance.
显然 我们这里有个可行性考虑 那就是碰撞避免
We can't drive somewhere if there is already a car there.
我们不能行驶到另一辆车的位置上
Then, for safety reasons,
然后 基于安全原因
we would want the buffer distance,
我们还要考虑缓冲距离
which tries to keep us far from other vehicles,
我们想离别的车辆远点
and the cost function which checks to make sure we are driving on
这里的成本函数将检测是否我们行驶在靠近道路中线的位置上
the road near the center of our lane and in a lane that's close to our goal lane.
并且 行驶车道是否靠近我们的目标车道
For acceleration, we'd first want to
对于加速度 我们首先考虑
make sure we only consider behaviors that the car can execute,
加速度的可行性
and then we'd want to avoid having any rapid changes in
其次 我们会尽量避免加速度的突然改变
acceleration because those are perceived as uncomfortable.
因为那会降低舒适性
This is also known as jerk which you'll learn more about in the next lesson.
加速度突变也被称为 Jerk 大家会在下一个课程里详细了解它
Consider a merge onto a highway, for example.
例如 我们来考虑车辆进入高速路的场景
This is a potentially dangerous situation where we really
这里可能存在潜在危险 所以我们特别希望
want to get up to traffic speed as quickly as possible.
尽快加速到道路车辆的平均速度上
So this cost function may become more relevant than it normally is.
所以此时这个成本函数也许变得比平时更加有意义
But we also want to make sure that we yield if there isn't really a gap,
但是 我们也想确保 如果没有空档 我们会等待机会
so we want to make sure this cost function and this one are weighted sufficiently high.
所以我们想要确保 这个成本函数在效率方面具有更高权重
And we can compare these merge priorities to a different situation.
我们可以把这些进入高速时的优先级同别的场景进行对比
For example, a car approaching a green light that suddenly turns yellow.
比如 一辆车行驶近绿灯时 灯突然变黄
In this situation, we'd probably want to boost the weights associated with
在这种情况下 我们可能想要加大合规性的权重
legality and would probably need to add
并可能需要增加一个全新的成本函数
a whole new cost function for obeying traffic rules.
以顺应交通法规
Now that doesn't fall neatly into the position,
现在 那个成本函数不属于我们目前的
velocity, or acceleration classes,
位置 速度 和加速度分类中
so I'll just put it over here.
所以我只是将它放在这里
If this is all starting to feel like it's getting pretty complex, well, you're right.
如果我们讨论的东西让你感觉有些复杂 那么 你的感觉非常正常
It's pretty hard to avoid this exploding complexity when using finite state machines.
当使用有限状态机的时候 要避免这些复杂性是相当困难的
Partially that's because of the finite state machine itself,
特别是 当原因是因为有限状态机本身的特性导致的时候
but we're also trying to solve a very hard problem and
但是 我们还是试图解决这种特别棘手的难题
some complexity is unavoidable no matter what solution approach you take.
但是 无论使用何种方法 有些复杂性确实是无法避免的